Stanford University
All right, I want to come to a new class
of systems.
It's a very interesting class of
systems. They're usually called magnets,
magnetic systems.
But they may or may not have anything to
do with genuine magnets.
Uh What is a magnet?
A magnet is a collection of little
magnets.
Okay?
And little magnets have the property
that they point along they tend to align
themselves along magnetic field.
But the important thing about them is
that they're little systems which can
point in any direction.
Furthermore,
whatever they are,
whether they're
uh um
little magnetic grains
or are they
iron atoms or something else,
they are themselves little magnets and
it means they're like
What do you call those things that
mariners use to figure out which way
they're going? Compasses, yes.
Uh they're little compasses except they
can point in three-dimensional space.
They have interactions between them.
And the interactions
tend to favor
parallel neighbors.
The interactions between them are fairly
short range, which means that roughly
speaking, each magnet affects its
nearest neighbors
and tends to make it want to align in
the same direction. That's the energy
function will tend to be lowest when the
magnets are aligned,
biggest when they're anti-aligned.
You can have the opposite, incidentally.
You can have the situation where the
little magnets
are
favor the energy favors anti-alignment.
Then it's not called a ferromagnet. A
ferromagnet is a situation where they
align. It's called an anti-ferromagnet
and it tends to make anti-alignment. But
real magnets, ferromagnets, iron magnets
are systems where the little magnets
tend to align each other.
But they only align their nearest
neighbors.
Okay.
Nevertheless, even though they only
align their nearest neighbors,
at sufficiently low temperature, it may
be the case that the fluctuations are
weak enough. At very high temperatures,
they fluctuate like mad. Okay? At very,
very low temperatures, only the lowest
energy states are important. And the
lowest energy states all have the
magnets aligned along the same
direction.
Which direction? Well, any direction,
but along the same direction.
So,
a ferromagnet is a system certainly
which at zero temperature, when there
are no fluctuations, tends to align and
it aligns by the first one aligning the
second one, second one aligning the
third one, third one aligning the fourth
one,
uh and so forth. Or really, we're not
thinking about a line of them. We may be
thinking about a three-dimensional block
of them. Each one aligning its neighbors
and the whole thing in some collective
way all pointing in the same direction.
As I said, at high temperatures, they
tend to fluctuate wildly.
And so it's not likely that at high
temperatures this phenomenon of
alignment will persist.
Okay?
All right. We make models. We make
various kinds of models of magnets,
mathematical models. The real thing, the
real genuine thing, a bunch of
interacting
uh uh iron atoms, is much too hard to
solve. If for no other reason
that the
interactions are not between just
nearest neighbors. There's a tendency
for the interaction to slop over to
second nearest neighbors, thirdly
nearest neighbors. And this makes a a
nightmare of a mathematical system
too complicated to solve in detail. So,
we make simplified models.
The first kind of simplified model is
called an Well,
the first kind of simplified model is
even so simplified that it doesn't have
any interaction between its neighbors.
All right. The first kind of magnet
we're going to study is not even really
a magnet. It has no interaction between
its neighbors.
But the simplifying the special
simplifying feature of it is this is a
kind This is a magnet whose little
individual magnets can only point in one
or two of two directions, either up or
down.
It's called a Z2 magnet. Why Z2? Z2 is
the group of two elements, up and down
basically, but that's not important to
us. It's called a Z2 magnet and most
studies or most of the early studies of
magnets were about Z2 magnets. All
right. So, that means we're building our
magnet out of little elements which have
only two possible states, either they're
up or they're down.
And we're making an array of them.
We might study different kinds of
models. We might study models in which
it's a one-dimensional array. We might
study two-dimensional arrays of them and
so forth and so on. Uh we might even
study very high-dimensional arrays, not
because anybody can build a
high-dimensional magnet, because the the
it's because the mathematics of
high-dimensional magnets turns out to be
especially simple for reasons I'll tell
you later.
All right. So, we have we have these
systems which are composed of these
elementary magnets
which are very simple. They either all
They either point up or they point down.
And in the
examples that we're ultimately want to
going to want to study,
there's an energy function which, let us
say, favors neighbors being in the same
direction. All right? So,
a high energy state would be
neighboring magnets in opposite
directions. A low energy state would be
neighboring magnets in the same
direction.
And so at zero temperature,
which will pick out the lowest energy
state, there are only two of them.
Either all magnets pointing up or all
magnets pointing down. All the little
elementary magnets pointing up or all
pointing down.
I'll assume for the moment that the
system is symmetric with respect to up
and down.
If it's symmetric with respect to up and
down, then the energy function, whatever
it is, between two neighboring magnets
will be
one thing if the two are parallel. In
other words, the same energy if they're
both up or they're both down.
And a higher energy if one is up and one
is down or one is down and one is up.
That's a simple system that we can try
to study.
An array of them, one-dimensional array,
two-dimensional array, three-dimensional
array. In fact, we could just study two
uh two atoms like this.
We'll call them spins. What they have to
do with spins? Nothing is spinning.
It's just a name for them, spins. And
the spin is either up or down.
And the energy favors having them
parallel.
So, at zero temperature, they will all
line up, either up or down.
But which is it going to be? Is it going
to be up or is it going to be down?
The answer is both are low energy
states. So, we can say
they're
Well, technically, we would say the
ground state is degenerate. Two possible
equal energy ground states or lowest
energy states.
But that means whether it's up or down
is going to depend on minute effects
such as, for example, a tiny, tiny stray
magnetic field.
A tiny, tiny stray By a tiny, tiny stray
magnetic field, I mean some almost
infinitesimally small magnetic field,
extremely small, which might even be too
small to measure, but still might favor
one direction or the other. There are so
many of these little magnets and they're
all in this infinitesimally small
magnetic field.
And so they all line up in that
direction. If we changed this
infinitesimally small magnetic field
from up to down, all the spins would
want to be down.
No matter how small that magnetic field
is,
the ground state will either be all up
or all down.
And if we imagine a limit in which that
background magnetic field gets smaller
and smaller and smaller, the
magnetization The magnetization means
the tendency for the all the spins to be
up or all the spins to be down it
doesn't
It just stays there until the external
magnetic field reverses sign and then
they might all simultaneously reverse
sign.
This is called spontaneous symmetry
breaking. The system has a symmetry.
What is a symmetry? You take all the
spins and you flip them.
You turn all ups to downs. If you take
turn all ups to downs, the energy stays
exactly the same, ignoring this little
stray field.
All ups have I mean, doesn't have They
don't have to all be up. Whatever the
configuration is,
it might be one up and one down. If you
turn them both over, you get one down
and one up, same energy. So, this system
has a symmetry.
The symmetry being Let's give these
Let's give these degrees of freedom a
name.
Let's call them sigma.
Sigma of I, the Ith spin.
Okay? And it's either plus or minus one.
Plus one if it's up, minus one if it's
down. All right? That's our system, a
collection of these simple degrees of
freedom.
The symmetry, here's the symmetry.
All sigmas, sigma sub i for all i
goes to minus sigma sub i.
All spins flip. Everything about the
system is exactly the same.
But,
if you put on the tiniest magnetic
field, it will tend to line it up in
that direction, and that direction is
not symmetric. And it's all up.
So, that's called spontaneous symmetry
breaking. Spontaneous means
that it doesn't go away as you shrink
the bias. We can think of the bias being
the tiny magnetic field which might bias
it in one direction.
We let that magnetic field get external
magnetic field get smaller and smaller
and smaller, and eventually we take it
away altogether, and the spins are left
all up. If we started with the magnetic
field in the opposite direction, the
external magnetic field in the opposite
direction, and then gradually removed
it, all the spins would be down. So,
there would be two possibilities,
but either of them would break the
symmetry. Breaking the symmetry means
that the configuration would not have
the symmetry of up goes to down, but it
would be biased in one direction or
another.
That's the phenomenon we want to study.
Now, another reason for studying it,
magnets are kind of interesting, of
course. We know they're they're lovely
little toys to play with.
But, another reason for studying these
kinds of systems
is because you can model an enormous
number of statistical mechanical systems
as magnets. Let me give you an example.
A gas,
a fluid. A fluid is a correct collection
of molecules.
Okay?
But, I can try to represent that
collection of molecules in the following
way. Break up
the container that that contains them
into
cells,
where the cells are about as big as a
molecule. Let's suppose these molecules
have hard cores, and that we can't
uh
stick them on top of each other.
Then, if the cells are about as big as a
molecule,
then we can't get two particles or two
molecules into a box.
And so, either a box is empty or it has
a molecule in it.
Again,
two possible states for each box. It's
either got a molecule or it don't got a
molecule. We could call having a
molecule up. We could call not having a
molecule down.
And then, this system of
molecules moving around, let's just put
uh let's put molecules in various boxes.
This would correspond
to a spin up, a spin down, down, down,
down, down, up over here, down
everywhere else. And we map the
mathematical problem of the gas of
molecules
into the mathematical problem of
the magnet.
That's a very, very fruitful avenue of
uh exploration, and it has been a
fruitful avenue of explanation.
And for example, uh let's pursue it.
Let's pursue it before we actually get
into the mathematics of it.
Let's uh
let's uh think about it a little bit.
What would correspond to the
configuration in which all the molecules
were up?
Full.
We absolutely chock-full this uh this
this system. We make the gas extremely
the gas We make the system extremely
dense.
What corresponds to all the uh spins
being down?
Empty.
So, the configuration with all molecules
up is the high density limit.
The
configuration with all molecule all
spins down, that's the low density limit
or the vacuum to be specific. But, let's
just call it the low density limit.
Okay?
What corresponds to a configuration
where there are equal numbers of ups and
downs?
For the magnet, we would call that
unmagnetized.
We would call it unmagnetized because on
the average every spin is equally likely
to be up and down. So, it's uh perhaps
the situation where there's enough
fluctuation to uh to um
uh to make on the average every spin be
zero. What would that correspond to to
this uh to this system here?
Half full. Half full. It would
correspond to the density half full.
Okay? Now, let's uh let's think about
what happens
to the magnet
when we have a little bit of a magnetic
field.
We have a little bit of a magnetic
field, and let's suppose it's some
finite temperature.
It's at some finite temperature, and we
put a little magnetic field which tends
to make it point down.
Okay?
All right. If it's at some finite
temperature, there will be some
fluctuation. All the molecules will not
literally point down. There will be some
fluctuation, but on the average uh
they'll point in the direction of the
magnetic field, but maybe with only a
weak bias. As the temperature goes up,
of course, the bias goes away, and they
tend to fluctuate more. So, at low
temperatures, but not zero temperatures,
what we'll find is that on the average
the magnets will be down, but not with a
full 100% magnetization.
And now, we start changing the magnetic
field a little bit, and we vary it.
It goes gets smaller and smaller and
smaller, the external magnetic field,
and finally becomes zero, but then we
turn it on with epsilon amount of a tiny
amount in the opposite direction. What
happens?
Well, if the magnet had spontaneous
magnetization, in other words, if this
phenomena of spontaneous symmetry to
symmetry spontaneous
symmetry breaking was active, then there
would be a sudden jump
in the magnetization.
A sudden jump from more spins down to
more spins up. What does that mean for
the fluid?
Well, the density. The density makes a
sharp jump. As we vary some parameter,
let's not worry about now exactly what
parameter to vary, but as we vary some
parameter, whatever the natural analog
of the magnetic field is, we'll find
it's the chemical potential in fact, but
as we vary some quantity, there's a
sudden change from a biased situation
where more spins are down. What does
that mean about the density?
Less than half.
To a jump where the density is more than
a half. What do we call that?
A phase transition. And it's a phase
transition from a less dense
configuration. We might give a name to
that. We might call it a gas.
To a more dense configuration. We might
give another name to that, a liquid.
Okay?
So,
just as an example, many, many systems
can be modeled
as these simple magnetic systems. We
call them magnetic systems, but uh they
stand for a lot of different kinds of
systems.
And that's why they're so useful.
They're useful for magnets, but they're
also useful for fluids.
The magnetic transition
where sudden spontaneous magnetization
happens, that's also the gas-liquid
phase transition.
So, that's why we study them. And we
don't just study them because they're
magnets, uh which are interesting in
their own right, but because they are a
broad brush description of many, many
different kinds of statistical
mechanical systems. I've given you two,
the magnet on the one hand, and what's
called the lattice gas on the other
hand.
The lattice gas is incidentally a uh
not always a gas. It can be a liquid or
a gas, depending on which phase it's in.
Uh let's uh let's ex- Before we actually
study such systems, let's uh talk about
them broadly first.
Let's make a plot.
And on this plot, let's plot temperature
on the horizontal axis.
Low temperature, everything fluctuates a
minimum amount. At zero temperature, it
just picks out the ground state.
At high temperatures, it that fluctuates
maximally. And on the vertical axis,
let's imagine an external magnetic
field. Let's see, we can put the whole
thing in a magnetic field. How can I
represent the magnetic field? Um
By an arrow with a different color.
Incidentally, we're restricting
ourselves to magnetic fields which are
either up or down.
Not not pointing sideways. So, we have
an external magnetic field.
Let's call it H.
Little H.
Why H? I don't know. It's a traditional
name for the magnetic field in these
spin systems.
h
Let's start at zero temperature.
No fluctuations.
What
happens
if h is pointing up?
Well, h will point up. It will bias all
of these spins and it will say they're
not fluctuating.
So, push them into their ground state,
but there were two ground states. The
low temperature will make them make sure
they're in the ground state.
But, there are two ground states, all up
or all down. Which one is going to be
favored?
Well, that will depend on the direction
of this magnetic field. This magnetic
field has a little bit of energy which
is different for an up and a down spin.
And so, if they're all up, that might be
the lowest energy.
So, when h is positive,
the let's call it the average
magnetization, the average is over the
spins,
it will be
magnetized upward. I don't know. Let's
just say the average of sigma
is uh greater than zero in this region.
magnetized up
And in this region where the magnetic
field is down,
Oh, where did I put my bag?
Uh sigma is
less than zero.
Now, it may or may not be,
but generally it is,
that if the temperature is low enough,
this state of affairs persists right up
to zero almost zero magnetic field.
And then across here, there's a jump.
A jump, sigma less than zero here,
and sigma greater than zero here.
So, there's a phase transition across
here. Let's just put a
uh
a bold line there of some kind.
And if we go across here, in other
words, if we fix the temperature, low
temperature,
and vary the external magnetic field,
there will be a jump of the
magnetization across here. That jump in
magnetization, as I said, corresponds to
a jump in the density of
the analog fluid here.
Now, this situation typically persists,
as we'll see,
out to some finite temperature.
And then, beyond that temperature,
the fluctuations in the system are so
strong that it destroys this tendency
for the spins to align themselves
when the external magnetic field goes to
zero.
They'll be aligned down here only
because of the presence of the external
magnetic field. They'll be aligned up
here because of the external magnetic
field.
But, right on the axis here, the net
magnetization, the net tendency to be up
or down, the net expectation value of
sigma will be zero along here.
And so, this jump will disappear and
everything will be completely consistent
of a completely um
uh smooth as you go across
here.
Again,
this here corresponds to the liquid
phase,
high density.
This corresponds to the gas phase, low
density.
If you fix the temperature,
you have a jump. Now, I'm going to tell
you what this h is. This h is actually
the chemical potential.
Corresponds to the chemical potential.
It's the thing that you use to vary the
density.
Of course, it's the thing that you use
to vary the density. The more you vary
the external magnetic field, the more
you'll bias it to either greater or
lesser density.
So, h is the chemical potential in the
analog, and if you want to vary the
density, you vary h. But, it varies
discontinuously at some point, and
that's the gas-liquid phase transition.
So, you can go to gas from gas to liquid
by crossing this boundary
and having a sudden jump in the density.
That's just the usual thing that happens
when
uh when there's a transition from vapor,
which is very low density,
to
liquid water, which is higher density.
But, you can also do something else. You
can go around here
and go from gas to liquid without
passing through any transition at all,
without passing through any
discontinuity at all.
That's called going around the critical
point.
And some of you who are familiar with
the properties of the gas-liquid phase
transition, know that you can go from
water to steam
without passing through a sudden abrupt
change by going around the critical
point. So, that corresponds to going
around the critical point. pointing
these things out just to show you that
this um
these lattice systems are
have a lot of physics in them, a lot of
familiar physics and sometimes some
unfamiliar physics.
Okay, we're going to study these lattice
systems a little bit. Yeah.
In in the case where you're talking
about the
magnetic system, Yeah.
you change that external magnetic field
a little bit. Let's say you're at very
low temperature. Yeah.
Uh is there a kind of a hysteresis
effect when you're right at at zero
field?
Yeah,
uh is there a hysteresis? You mean if
you go around in a loop? Well, no, not
if you go around the loop, but if you
just uh keep the temperature down below
the critical point there.
Do you have to because you've got some
interactions between all these
Yeah. spins. Yeah.
Do you have to put a little
extra field on there? You're asking
whether there's a metastable phase.
You're asking whether you can have
metastability,
the analog of what happens if you were
to lower the temperature of uh of steam
below the uh below the below the
temperature of the transition, and
you're very, very careful, can you keep
it steam?
I think that's what you're asking.
Yeah, I think
that's the issue with metastability.
Metastability.
Can you vary this h and go down to here
keeping all the spins upward? And the
answer is typically yes, but if you sit
there, it's not true equilibrium.
It's not true equilibrium. If you take a
a system, let's take these little
magnets, all right? Now, we've ignored
the question of what causes the magnets
to change their direction.
All we've done is talk about their
orientation. We haven't talked about uh
the kinetic energies which might
cause them to to actually move.
But, let's imagine that there was
something in the system which caused
them to move. All right.
So, you start with a magnetic field
downward, they point downward. And then
you very, very carefully increase the
magnetic field,
and you will come to a point, if you're
very, very careful with the magnet,
where the magnet will be pointing in the
wrong direction relative to the field.
That's called a metastable situation.
But, if you sit there and you wait there
long enough, sooner or later,
a fluctuation will happen.
A fluctuation will happen.
Uh one of the spins will realize, or a
group of them, a small group of them,
will realize that they can find lower
energy configuration by flipping
themselves over.
And once they flip themselves over, that
thing starts spreading out
and creates a bubble of uh
of um
spins
which all then write themselves and get
themselves oriented in the right
direction. So, it's called
metastability. It's not really
equilibrium. It's out of equilibrium,
but it can take a long, long time for
equilibrium to set in. And that's the
root of metastability of metastability.
Um
Yes, that can happen, and it's closely
connected to the phenomena of
metastability in the gas-liquid system,
where you can cool or otherwise change
the parameters of a gas-liquid phase
transition gas-liquid system, where you
might be able to
one way or another,
very carefully change the liquid or
change the parameters so that you move
into what should be the gas region, but
nevertheless, the system not budge and
stay liquid. But, if you sit there and
wait a little bit,
sooner or later, a little bubble of gas
will form, and then the bubble of gas
will uh will take over the whole system.
Is that supercooling or superheating?
Yeah.
So, question? Yeah, it's connected with
hysteresis. Yeah.
My question is, in the case of you said
this is Z2, but in case of
these magnets, so wouldn't you flip
them?
A normal magnet would radiate energy
away, we
Yeah. We're ignoring that aspect. Yeah,
yeah, we're not asking we're not asking
about the kinetics of the system. Right.
Right.
But, I'll tell you all right, but you
can ask what really do you still you can
ask what really does happen to magnets.
Now, real magnets are of course not
these Z2 magnets. They are
Right.
So, you could you could imagine trying
to orient the magnets with a magnetic
field, change the magnetic field to get
into an unstable situation,
but then typically what happens is after
a while, they'll start to slosh around
uh and yeah, what they'll radiate away
as spin waves.
Spin waves are sort of waves of wiggly
magnetization. But, there are no spin
waves for this situation because they're
either all locked up well, everyone is
either up or down, and no ways in
between. so
Uh
Yeah, they could flip, for example, by
emitting sound waves. They could flip by
emitting light waves, but that would be
unusual for a real magnet. A real magnet
doesn't flip itself over
when a compass changes direction, it
usually doesn't emit lightning bolt. I
mean, it uh
it might emit a little tiny bit of sound
into the
Not much.
Well, very
Even that would be hard since the
Yeah, very right. Very, very low
frequency radio waves.
Right. More likely just some sound waves
or something, which is easier to But uh
or some pressure waves or who knows. I
don't know.
Um Anyway, this is This is the what we
want to study.
I'm not going to study these things in
as much mathematical detail
as I do in the notes that I've
distributed to you.
I'm trying to decide
Yeah, I think what I'll do
is give you an illustration
of
the phenomena
phenomenon of spontaneous magnetization
in an approximation which is called the
mean field approximation.
This is one of the many approximations
I'll tell you the various approximations
that we apply to these kind of magnetic
systems.
Uh there are approximations which are
called low temperature expansions
where you begin with a system at zero
temperature and you expand your way in
powers of something involving the
temperature.
All right.
There are high temperature expansions
where you start the system at the
infinite temperature where it fluctuates
like mad and then you expand about one
over the temperature. High temperature
expansions. They're not very hard and
they're not very difficult uh but it's
not where we're going to go. Then
there's another kind of method called
renormalization group. That's a method
that I will maybe tell you a little bit
about as we go along,
but not tonight.
And the other method is called mean
field approximation.
And mean field approximation is a nice
physically intuitive picture of how this
phenomena of magnet of spontaneous
magnetization takes place.
That's what I want to do tonight is show
you the mean field description of this.
And mean here doesn't mean nasty. It
doesn't mean cheap. It means average.
Okay? Mean field approximation.
Now, what we're going to imagine is that
we have a lattice.
And it might be a three-dimensional
lattice, which might be the case we're
really interested in, or it might be a
two-dimensional lattice.
Uh we I don't want to deal with the
one-dimensional lattice for reasons that
perhaps we'll discuss. But let's start
with either a two-dimensional lattice
that I can draw on the blackboard or a
three-dimensional lattice or better yet,
a
D that D D like David, a D-dimensional
lattice.
And the reason I say a D-dimensional
lattice is because this approximation
works best when D is very large for
reasons that I'll explain.
The reason is very simple.
The reason has to do with the fact that
the higher the dimension, the more
neighbors that any given
atom has or any given site has.
In one dimension, each site only has two
neighbors.
Okay? In a thousand dimensions, how many
How many How many neighbors does a
thousand have?
2,000 neighbors Uh
Yeah.
2,000 neighbors in a thousand
dimensions. In two dimensions, each one
has four neighbors.
In three dimensions, two more, six
neighbors.
So, 2D neighbors.
Now, the reason it's good to have a lot
of neighbors is because you can average
over the neighbors.
You can
You can do an average over the neighbors
and say this molecule at the center sees
the effect of a large number of
neighbors and it doesn't matter much if
one neighbor change this is a little bit
different. You can average over the
neighbors. You can use the laws of large
numbers, so to speak, statistics
to average over the properties of the
nearest neighbors. So, it's as if
we in this room
formed a lattice, which you do form
sitting there in your chairs, although
it's a rather irregular lattice.
And you're interested in the properties
of the neighbors and what your neighbors
are doing to you.
Well,
if there are enough neighbors, you can
average over them and say the effect of
my nearest neighbors on me is to have
this particular effect, which is the
average over large numbers of neighbors.
If there's only one or two neighbors,
then averaging over them might be a less
effective thing to do. And this is true
for this kind of system. So,
the mean field approximation becomes
accurate, infinitely accurate or
perfectly accurate in the limit of large
numbers of dimensions. But we're not
really interested in the limit of large
number of dimensions. Well, it turns out
numerically
that two
is a little bit large and three is large
already. In other words, mean field
approximation works pretty well for
three dimensions.
But more important than whether it works
numerically well is it gives you a
picture of what happens
that leads to this magnetization.
All right. Now, we're going to invent
now an energy function.
An energy function
uh
which
is the energy function
well, for this system of atoms. Each one
is either up or down. Let's represent an
up by a dot and a down by a cross.
The energy only depends on
the on the orientation configuration of
nearest neighbors.
All right?
The energy is low when they're parallel
and high when they're anti-parallel.
So, here's an expression which does
that.
Let's take the energy
to just be
Let's call it sigma of I sigma of J, but
now I and J represent neighboring points
on the lattice.
As you range over I and J, I really only
want you to imagine that you're ranging
over nearest neighbors.
Nearest neighbors
uh on the lattice.
And let's put a minus sign in here.
Now, if sigma I and sigma J are the
same,
in other words, if they're both plus one
or minus one,
then sigma I sigma J is one and the
energy is negative. Negative is low.
All right. So, this favors or lowers the
energy when they're parallel. What about
when they're anti-parallel? When they're
anti-parallel,
then the energy is
plus one.
And so, there's two units of energy
stored
in every
bond if the bond is a broken bond. Now,
what do I mean by a broken bond? Let's
say an unbroken bond
is a bond where the spins are parallel.
Here's an unbroken bond. A bond means a
nearest neighbor link of the lattice.
Here's another bond which is unbroken.
The spins are parallel at the two ends
of it.
A broken bond
would be one
like this one over here where the spins
are anti-parallel.
Broken bonds cost you energy.
Uh how much energy? Each broken bond
costs you two units of energy.
So, energetically, it's profitable to
keep the number of broken bonds to a
minimum. But on the other hand, as you
raise the temperature,
because there are so many possible
configurations with broken bonds,
raising the temperature will tend to
create a population of broken bonds
there. All right. So, that's that's the
picture.
Now, we're going to do an interesting
approximation which really captures some
of the interesting physics.
Let's focus on one molecule.
Let's focus on this molecule right over
here. I
I've
I don't know whether it's up or down, so
I haven't biased it, but let's focus on
this one over here.
And let's write the expression for its
energy.
Its energy
Let's call this Let's call this sigma
zero. That's sigma zero. Right at the
center,
the spin that I focus in on is called
sigma zero. It's plus one or minus one.
And it interacts with all of its nearest
neighbors. So, its energy, the energy of
sigma zero, let's call it Let's call it
little E. Little E represents the energy
of this spin
in the background of all of its
neighbors. And what is it? It's minus
sigma zero times
the sum of all the spins of all the
nearest neighbors.
Sum over nearest neighbors
of the nearest neighbor spins. I'm not
going to try to make too much That's
enough terminology, enough uh enough
indexology.
Okay?
Let's suppose
that
the spins have an average value.
Okay? An average value that the system
is magnetized.
Uh let's suppose. It may not be. We'll
find out if it's not. In other words,
let's suppose that on the average
each spin
has the same value as each other spin,
and let's suppose on the average the
average of any spin
is called S.
Now, S is a number between -1 and 1. The
average of a thing which can only be 1
or -1 must lie between 1 and -1.
So, whatever S is
the average spin is between 1 and -1. S
is the thing which is called the mean
field, the average field, the average
value of all of the spins.
And now each one of these spins sees
around it a whole bunch of spins. If the
dimensionality of the system is high
enough, it sees loads and loads of spins
around it.
And so it has some average energy in the
background. This one has an energy in
the background of all of these.
Right? And what is its its energy? It's
just equal to - sigma naught
times Now, on the average each one of
these sigmas is equal to S. So, that's N
or sorry, that's twice D
times S. Why twice D?
That's because that's the number of
nearest neighbors. Twice D is the number
of nearest neighbors.
So, I replaced each one of these by its
average. There are 2D of them. And so
that particular spin right at the center
is experiencing
a bias
or a effective energy which is
proportional to that spin
uh with a minus sign, whatever it is.
Now, S can either be positive or
negative. We don't know offhand whether
S is positive or negative.
They may all be They may have a tendency
They may be zero. Maybe on the average S
is equal to zero.
Then
this would not be magnetized.
It's magnetized if S is not zero.
And S can either be positive or it can
be negative or it can be zero. And
that's what we want to find out. But
let's assume that there's some finite
value of S.
Now that we know the energy of this
particular spin
in the background of all the others
let's just do some statistical mechanics
for this one spin
in the background of all the others.
We're freezing all the others Well,
we're not freezing them. We're freezing
their average value. And we're going to
think of sigma naught as a little system
all by itself
at temperature T.
And let's see what we can learn about
it.
Let me not call it sigma naught anymore.
Let me just call it sigma.
It's just the one spin that I'm focused
on now.
And it has an energy
its energy E stands for energy now
which is equal as I wrote over there
twice the dimensionality of space
S
That's not DS, that's just
D times S.
It doesn't stand for the differential of
S.
times sigma.
And let's write the partition function
and the statistic
Yes.
Let's write the statistical mechanics
for that spin.
The probability
function for it is e to the minus beta
times its energy.
But its energy is just this. So, that
gives us a plus
2 D S
times sigma.
That's the Boltzmann weighting factor.
Next let's calculate the partition
function.
Okay? The partition function is the sum
over the two possible configurations of
the spin.
We're just doing the both the the
probability the um
the probability distribution for the
single spin in the field of all the
others. And so let's just write that
this is equal This is the sum over sigma
sigma equals plus or minus one.
And so what do we get?
We get
that the partition function is just
equal to e
to the twice Let's twice
beta
D
S
plus e to the minus 2 beta D S.
I've just added the two configurations,
and this is the partition function for
this very simple system
in the field of all the others.
Okay? That's Z.
How do I calculate the average energy
of this spin?
Well, we first have to take a logarithm.
Right. All right. This is also twice the
the hyperbolic cosine
of
2 beta D S.
Okay, that's uh that step.
Let's take its logarithm.
Log of Z
is equal to first of all log of 2
plus
log
of
cosh
2 beta
D S.
What about the um minus the log of Z is
of course just this.
Now, what is the energy? The energy is
the derivative of minus log Z with
respect to beta.
That's the thermodynamic identity or the
statistical mechanics identity we've
used over and over.
So
the energy, but not the energy of the
whole system now just the energy of this
one spin.
I'll just call it What shall we call it?
Uh
Well
basically it's the average value of
little e here.
The average value of this little spin
is or it's the average value of the
energy of this one spin. What is it
given by? It's given by the derivative
of minus log Z. Let's see. So, what is
that? That's minus
one over hyperbolic cosine of 2 beta D
S.
And then we have to differentiate the
hyperbolic cosine with respect to beta.
That gives us hyperbolic sine.
2 beta D S. And then we have to
differentiate what's in here with
respect to beta, so that gives us
another factor of 2
uh D times S.
Okay.
This is the important factor over here.
It has another name. It's minus the
hyperbolic tangent
of 2 beta D S.
Okay.
That's the answer
for the
average energy.
But what about the average value of the
spin itself?
What about the average value of sigma
itself?
Well, the energy of sigma
is sigma minus sigma times 2 D times S.
If I wanted the average of sigma, I
would just take the average of the
energy and divide it by 2 D S.
Spin and energy just differ by a factor
of minus 2 D S.
So, if I simply divide the average
energy by 2 D S, I will find the average
value of the spin.
What is that? Here's 2 D Here is Well,
let's see.
I think I I think I left out something.
Yeah, here it is. 2 D S.
times 2 D S.
If we just cancel this 2 D S
then we have the average value of the
spin. I think I also want to cancel the
minus sign.
That's the average value of that spin
by doing statistical mechanics on that
spin.
Incidentally
if you plot hyperbolic tangent
the function hyperbolic tangent
if we plot beta this way
and hyperbolic tangent vertically
it looks something like this.
It goes to one at this end and minus one
at this end.
What does this correspond to?
The maximum value that tanh takes on is
one.
The minimum value that it takes on is
minus one. This just corresponds to the
statement that at
uh at
that the maximum value the average of
the spin can take on is one and minus
one.
This end here
or both ends actually are low
temperature when beta goes to zero. So,
when beta goes to zero, sorry, when beta
goes to infinity. When beta goes to
infinity, that's low temperature.
And don't ask me about this side over
here. I'm going to come to that side
over here. It's a little weird, isn't
it? What does that mean?
Negative temperature. Weird, huh?
Yeah, okay.
We'll we'll come to negative
temperature, but let's
uh
But this is the average value of the
spin
uh as a function of beta.
The spin is a function of beta. All
right. Um
Yeah, you could relabel
It's interesting if you relabel the
x-axis
um
S and you get the same shape.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, we're going to do that
in a minute, right?
Um
Good.
All right. So, this is the average of
the spin.
But now,
this only makes sense
if the average value of the spin over
here is the same as all of the other
spins.
After all, we're assuming that every
spin is like every other spin.
And so, we have a consistency
requirement. The consistency requirement
is just that this average value of the
spin here
be equal
to the average value of the spin.
S. And this becomes an equation
for
if you like the magnetization, the
magnitude of the magnetization, S
itself. S is the average of the spin,
it's the amount of magnetization.
And this becomes a self-consistency
equation. Let's just go back. What did
we do? We said, "Look, in the limit of a
large number of nearest neighbors, we
can average over the nearest neighbors
and just think of an average behavior
of the nearest neighbors.
Assume that the nearest neighbors on the
average have a spin S, then the energy
of our friend at the center here will be
minus sigma times 2 DS. And now knowing
that, let's use the statistical
mechanics to calculate the average value
of S. And once we've done it,
consistency requires that it just be the
same as the input S in the first place.
So, here we are.
What do I have to do? We have to satisfy
this equation.
On the left, we have S. Let's draw the
graph of just S.
All right, we can put S over here.
tanh 2 beta S
uh is
uh we put S on the horizontal axis.
What is the significance in this terms
of this graph of changing beta Let's say
D is fixed. D is three dimensions now.
What's the significance of changing
beta?
It changes the slope at the origin here.
All right, that's all. It just spreads
the curve out or shrinks it together.
What happens when beta is very small?
It spreads it out
like this.
So, this is beta small.
Well, that's not that's not the axis.
This just stands for small beta.
What about large beta?
Supposing beta was enormously large.
Yeah.
It means it looks almost like
this.
But these curves This curve and that
curve are related to each other. They're
just shrinking along one axis.
Squeezing it along Well, I didn't quite
do it right. The height of this should
have been the same as the height of
this.
This corresponds to one unit over here.
This is one unit over here.
All right. So, I didn't draw it well,
but that's the picture. Now, let's draw
S as a function of S. On the left-hand
side, we have S. On the right-hand side,
we have this tanh. We want to set them
equal. That just means superimposing on
this diagram
a straight line.
At the point where they intersect, S
will be equal to tanh 2 beta S.
All right, what about here?
Where do they intersect?
They only intersect at the origin.
That's the only place where they
intersect is at the origin.
And the implication of that is there's
only one solution of the equation. And
that one solution of the equation is
magnetization equal to zero.
Okay? That's what happens at small beta.
And small beta means high temperature.
Now, you start lowering the temperature.
And as you lower the temperature, this
curve migrates to this curve. And what
happens over here?
Now, there are actually three solutions.
There are three solutions.
And to calculate which solution is
actually the right solution, you have to
calculate the entropy and see which one
corresponds to the highest entropy.
All right? Turns out these two have the
same entropy. And this one is some
higher entropy configuration, which
actually corresponds to some kind of
metastable configuration.
Here is Here is the
solution.
Another way you can do it is to imagine
that there is this little weak magnetic
field. If there was a very tiny small
magnetic field, it would bias you to one
of these two solutions
depending on which way. Incidentally,
these two solutions correspond to the
two possibilities for the magnetization,
either all either on the average up or
the average down. They correspond to S
equals something positive or something
negative.
All right? If you were to bias the
system with a little bit of external
magnetic field and really work it out
carefully, you would find out that the
only these two solutions persist.
That's all that's there. And that's what
happens. So, what happens now? You start
changing the temperature.
And at some point
at some point the slope of the tanh
function here gets to be equal to the
slope of the straight line here. And
after that, there's the intersection
that corresponds to the magnetized
phase.
Where does that happen? That happens
when the slope of this function becomes
equal to one.
That's just when
twice DS
uh sorry, twice
when twice beta D
is equal to one.
When twice beta D is equal to one,
then the tanh curve here
becomes equal in slope
to the straight line.
And beyond that,
it has this new intersection over here
and over here.
That's where the magnetization happens.
So,
in effect, we have found the
temperature,
the beta,
at which this phenomena first happens.
It happens Let's see, what is it? It's
when beta
is bigger.
We have spontaneous magnetization. This
is spontaneous magnetization.
Yeah.
When Let's see, beta, which is one over
the temperature,
times 2D is equal to one or temperature
equals
twice the dimension of space.
All right. Twice that The temperature
equal to twice the dimension of space.
Whatever in space would be three for
three-dimensional system. So, at a
temperature of six units and
uh
six units in what unit? Well,
uh we would need to put some units in
here by putting a constant into this
formula over here. This is not
dimensionally consistent. Sigma is
either plus or minus one.
And energy has units of energy. We have
to throw in another constant over T to
uh to give it units.
That other constant would appear over
here.
Yeah, let's call that constant J. I
always call that constant J.
Then it would appear over here and has
units of energy.
Okay.
The main point is you see what the
pattern is that as you vary the
temperature
from high temperature to low temperature
or from low temperature to high
temperature,
let's start at the low temperature
situation.
At the very lowest temperatures,
at the very lowest temperatures, this is
a sharp jump here.
And what does it say? It says the
magnetization is either plus one or
minus one. So, at temperature equal to
zero, it's just temperature equal to
zero, T.
You jump
Well,
you jump
as you go across here
from magnetization minus one
to plus one.
Two possible solutions. And then, as you
increase the temperature, let's see what
happens as you increase the temperature.
If you increase the temperature to a
high enough point
beyond to a temperature higher than
this,
there's no more solution other than the
solution
at zero.
Okay? So, that means as you increase the
temperature, at some point
at some point, the spontaneous
magnetization disappears.
The spontaneous symmetry breaking
disappears, and there's only the
solution with sigma equal to zero.
No uh
no magnetization over here.
But, up to that point, there is
magnetization. So, we have exactly the
situation that I described when we
began.
And we have a jump
a jump in the magnetization
uh that's associated with a jump from
here to here.
If we bias the system a little bit with
a little bit of external magnetic field,
one of the two of these will be the
lower energy configuration, and it will
dominate the the uh physics.
All right. So, that's the
that's the phenomena of spontaneous
magnetization. One other point,
notice what happens to the intersection
over here
as
you go
to this point over here. As you go to
this point over here, let's track it.
So, let's start with uh
Okay. So, here's
here's very low temperature.
And now, we raise the temperature,
this curve
starts to move over to this, like that.
This point moves down. And as we lower
the temperature, we eventually come to
this first point where the crossover is,
and the crossover
the cross the crossing of the two curves
migrates continuously to the origin
here. And the meaning of that
is that the there's magnetization all
along here. In other words, there's
non-zero average
of the spin,
but as you move toward this point here,
the average magnetization goes away, and
disappears at that point, and then it's
gone.
Okay. What's this point called? Anybody
know?
Critical point. Curie point, yeah.
Critical point.
T critical.
Right.
What would it mean for a fluid?
What does it mean for the gas-liquid
phase transition?
It means that as you move to the
critical point, the density difference
between the gas
and the liquid goes to zero. Over here,
more spins down.
Over here, more spins up. There's a gap,
a separation in the value of the density
as you jump from here to here. But, as
you go above the critical point, or
right to the critical point,
right at that point, the liquid and the
gas density are exactly the same.
And then beyond that, there is no
liquid-gas distinction.
Okay? At temperatures higher than the
critical temperature.
So, that's the uh that's the that's the
mean field approximation to the
critical point of uh
of the Ising magnet. I didn't tell you,
this is called the Ising magnetic uh
system. Ising, I S I N G.
Ising didn't invent it.
He solved the one-dimensional version of
it, which takes about a quarter of a
line of paper.
It's it's very trivial.
His thesis advisor used to ask him to
study it as a example of phase
transitions,
and he did. And he discovered that
there's no phase transition in one
dimension. Now, that doesn't seem
consistent with this.
When D equals 1, this still seems to be
the same phenomena, but the point is in
one dimension, it's a poor
approximation. There aren't enough
nearest neighbors to average over. He
solved it correctly, and found there was
no phase transition.
Uh
And from that, he concluded that there
are no phase transitions, period.
He was quite wrong.
But, he did get his name to be the most
famous name in statistical mechanics,
because he uh
his thesis advisor happened to give him
the right problem.
Anyway,
uh the Ising model is all these are
called the Ising models.
And in dimensions higher than one, the
mean field approximation is a good
approximation, and says that there's a
critical point, magnetization up to that
critical point, no magnetization after
that, and the magnetization smoothly
goes to zero as you go to the critical
point.
All right. So, that's uh
I uh this took shorter than I expected
it to. So, let's uh have some questions.
And I don't want to start I don't want
to start a new topic now, yeah.
Oh, J is just a constant. Uh
let's just go back to where it came
from. I wrote that the energy of the
system
was minus sigma I sigma J. Yeah.
Now, sigma is a dimensionless variable.
It takes on magnitude 1 and minus 1. So,
it's dimensionless. So, this is not
dimensionless dimensionally consistent
if I wanted to restore some dimensions.
So, what I would do is I would put a
constant here with units of uh of an
energy. Okay. All right? J, I suppose J
for joule, I don't know.
Uh
and then it would reappear over here.
Cuz it uh it always multiplies the
dimensionality of
space, right?
Could you go
the logic again for S equals to tangent
hyperbolic 2 beta S? Well, what we find
what we find
when we isolate this one spin, and think
of it
in the background of all the others,
is that it's average in the background
because because of thermal fluctuations
will be tangent to beta d S.
All right? Now, that's just one spin out
of all these others.
What we've assumed
is that there's an average spin for
every spin on the lattice, which are all
the same. Every spin is like every other
spin. And we've assumed that the average
spin is equal to S.
That was our starting point. We replaced
all the nearest neighbors by S.
But, then this is only consistent if
when we calculate the average of any one
of the spins, it's equal to the average
that we
assumed in the beginning.
So, we assumed an average value
for all the other spins.
We then calculated the expectation or
the average value of the one spin that
we treated honestly.
All the others we just treated as
averageable, as something we can
average.
This one spin we treated honestly in the
background of the others,
and we found out that at a given
temperature, it has an average
which is equal to this.
The only consistency the only consist
the only way this can be consistent,
since we assumed that the average of a
spin is equal to we called it S, is for
these two to be equal.
So, it's just the consistency of
um the original assumption that the
average of the spin is equal to S.
And this is a Incidentally, this method
of mean field is a common method in
physics,
where when you have a lot of degrees of
freedom,
you focus on one of them,
and you assume the average value for all
the others.
Then, using the average value for all
the others, you study the dynamics of
the one additional degree of freedom,
and then in the end,
when you've calculated the averages for
that one additional degree of freedom,
set them equal to the averages that you
assumed for all the others. That's
called the mean field approximation.
And as I said, it's a it's a
uh
it's a widely used approximation,
and it is most effective in situations
where any one degree of freedom is in
direct contact with a large number of
others that you can average over.
In terms of the dimensionality of space,
it means that uh the uh what's called
the coordination number, the number of
nearest neighbors, is large.
The way you can get the number of
nearest neighbors to be large, there's
only one way, and that's to let the
dimension of the lattice get large.
So, uh so then you have the perfect
right to ask, "Okay, you've convinced us
about something in the limit of very
large numbers of dimensions. We might
believe it for a thousand dimensions. We
might even believe it for a hundred
dimensions.
We might even believe it for 10
dimensions. But, where should we start
to disbelieve it?"
And the answer is you should start It
depends, of course, on the degree of of
accuracy you want.
But, if you want something like 20%
accuracy, or you just want uh you know,
20% accuracy for the critical
temperature, then okay. D equals 3 is
fine. It's a good approximation for D
equals 3.
It's a so-so approximation for D equals
2.
I'll tell you the exact numbers. If you
calculate the critical temperature,
here's the critical temperature. Where
was it? Um
Setting J equal to 1, here it is.
Setting J equal to 1.
All right.
For
two dimensions, T is equal to 4 in some
appropriate units.
The correct answer, if I remember, is
about 2.7.
So, it's not good and it's not horrible.
For three dimensions, I don't remember
the exact numbers. Of course, I can do
uh I can do 2 * 3. That I'm pretty good
at. It's six.
But, I don't remember the exact Let's
see. Um
the critical temperature is always
lower. The real critical temperature is
always lower than the mean field
approximation.
Um
so, I I don't remember the exact
numbers, but it's, you know, it's within
20% of the uh 15% of the right answer.
And by D equals Well, we're not
interested. We're really not interested
in four dimensions, five dimensions, and
six dimensions. It's reasonably accurate
for D equals three. Uh gives you the
right uh the right general picture and
uh is even quantitatively within about
15%. I can't remember the exact number.
D equals one, it completely breaks down.
The critical Well, it uh completely
breaks down. It says T equals 2D. The
actual answer is T equals zero.
The critical temperature is zero.
In other words, you never even really
get started. At temperature zero, it's
true that there's a that there's a
magnetized phase, either all up or all
down, but the smallest amount of
temperature will disrupt it.
Incidentally, I can tell you the
physical reason for that.
There's an an interesting simple
physical reason
why
you can't have this kind of
spontaneous order in
uh in one dimension
and why you can have it in higher
dimensions.
Let's think about all of the
configurations
of the one-dimensional theory.
Let's start with all spins up.
So, what we're starting with
is a little bit of bias, which makes all
the spins be up.
And now, let's look at all the
configurations that we can build on top
of that. What can we do? We can start
flipping spins down. What happens? How
much energy is stored in one spin
flipped down? Can anybody figure that
out?
Hm?
Four.
Four. Each bond Each broken bond costs
you two units of energy. You have to go
from minus one to plus one.
So, each broken bond costs you two units
of energy. This costs four units of
energy.
How about flipping two spins down?
Are they next to each other? Very good.
Are they next to each other? Are they
not? What if they're not next to each
other? Then, the answer is eight. But,
what if they are next to each other?
Four again.
What if they are three apart?
Four.
There's an infinite number of
configurations
which cost you no more
in energy than just one flipped spin.
Whole big blocks of them, flipping them
over, cost you no more energy than one
of them.
That's the main reason why the
magnetized phase is unstable
when you increase the the temperature a
little bit. There's just a lot of
configurations
which cost the minimum amount of excess
energy.
What happens in higher dimensions? Let's
take higher dimensions.
Let's take two dimensions.
Again, start with all spins up.
And now, flip one of them over. How much
energy does that cost?
Eight units of energy.
How about two units?
How about two spins flipped?
16 if they're far from each other,
but how much if they're next to each
other?
12. Let's see which which are the broken
bonds.
Here's a broken bond.
Let's just color green the broken bonds.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five, six. This is not a broken bond
over here.
So, that's 6 * 2 is 12 units of energy.
That's more energy than just one flipped
spin.
Okay?
Here's the way you can count.
Draw a perimeter around the islands of
flipped spins. Imagine flipping islands
of spins. Imagine islands or groups of
them adjacent
flipped
and draw
a boundary around them
like that. And then, count how many
bonds this boundary passes through.
How many? Well, it's proportional to
But, the main thing is there's no way to
flip a lot of spins without costing a
lot of energy.
The cheapest you can do, if you want to
flip 100 spins, the cheapest in energy
is to have them form
a compact group of them.
Well, probably not a square. Probably uh
yeah, maybe a square.
Maybe a square.
And then, the number of broken bonds is
proportional to the surface Well, it's
proportional to the boundary.
Right? It's in one dimension,
boundary is just two points.
And so, when you flip whole blocks of
spins, it just breaks two bonds. But, in
higher dimensions, trying to flip large
numbers of spins becomes costly because
you have to break a lot of bonds. The
number of bonds does not grow as fast as
the number of spins, but it does get
bigger and bigger. And that's why
there's this stability to uh to the
higher dimensions
to the magnetization in higher
dimensions than there is in two
dimensions.
Uh because every island of spins is
surrounded by a bunch of neighbors which
are holding it fixed.
And to flip large numbers of them
becomes costly, whereas in two
dimensions,
big blocks of spins are only held in
place by two bonds.
Not a very stable situation.
Uh the technical mathematics of it, we
can uh postpone to another time. But,
that's the intuitive physics of what's
going on.
So, in fact, you could conclude from
this that there's no gas-liquid phase
transition in one dimension, and there
isn't.
There is a gas-liquid phase transition
in two dimensions. Now, who's interested
in one dimension and two dimensions?
Well,
it turns out that there are lots of
systems in in solid-state mechanics
where solid-state physics and condensed
matter physics
which are approximately in some sense
either one-dimensional or
two-dimensional systems. Systems of uh
you know, uh
long chains of molecules or planes or
flat planes of molecules.
And uh these
lower-dimensional systems do have a real
utility, a real application.
But, as I said, in one dimension and two
dimen- one dimension, there is no
uh gas-liquid or magnetic phase
transition. In two dimensions and
higher, there is. And in very high
dimensions, mean field approximation
becomes extremely accurate.
So, this is like This is only for
lattice systems?
Well, the the tools that I showed you
were for lattice systems.
Uh
there's more general systems that we
could study. Incidentally, it's kind of
fun to try to do a better approximation
than the simple mean field
approximation. And here's the game. You
again pretend that all the spins are
equal to S.
But, then you unfreeze two of them. Not
just one of them. You unfreeze two of
them, and you study the statistical
mechanics of pairs of them.
Two of them free to fluctuate. Two
adjacent ones free to fluctuate. And you
calculate in the background of all the
others, the average value of any one
spin of either of the two of these.
Okay? You do that, and then you set the
average value of either one, they'll be
the same, equal to the background spin,
and you get a better approximation. You
get a better approximation because
you've allowed one nearest neighbor to
each one of them to fluctuate, and you
get a better approximation. It's an
improvement. You can go further. You can
study three spins at a time in the
background of all the others. You get an
even better approximation.
Okay? Eventually, you can study all the
spins in the background of no spins, and
you get the exact answer.
But, it is fun. I once worked out the
two-spin case in the background of the
others, and you do get a numerically
quite a quite a good answer for the
three-dimensional case. I know you said
negative temperatures are interesting.
Oh oh well, yeah. Let's come to negative
temperature the next time.
Yeah. How did they figure out this
number? We could We didn't have to think
of this as negative temperature. We
could just think of it as negative S.
Okay. Right. That was That was the right
way to think about it.
How did they get the exact number? You
said they had an exact number. This is
an exactly solvable uh Oh, okay. All
right.
Comparing high temperature expansions
and low temperature expansions and
discovering that they are very close
Well, something called lattice duality.
Which you will find written up in the
notes that I distributed
uh on the internet.
The lattice duality uh argument. And
it's a very elegant, beautiful
mathematical observation about these
systems, but I
uh I
didn't want to do it here.
But, this two-dimensional system
the two-dimensionalizing model is
exactly solvable.
It has enough symmetry and enough
special structure
uh
that it is exactly solvable.
Is there a name for this the
two-free
element solution? For this? For Yeah.
No, the You mean the mean field with two
spins unfrozen?
Is that what you're asking? Yes. Not
that I know of.
Is something called the beta
approximation? To which? Um this is beta
approximation. Beta? Beta? Yes. Beta?
Hans Beta? No, that's not that that's
got nothing to do with this. That's got
That is one-dimensional systems, but not
the Ising model. Ising model is too
simple. I mean, if you apply the beta
approximation, it would be like hitting
a uh
a peanut with a with a sledgehammer. Um
no, the uh it's for one-dimensional
systems, and it's for one with
one-dimensional systems with more
complicated kinds of interactions which
cause them to uh
what are called Heisenberg magnets.
That's not the Ising ma- magnet.
He first worked out the beta approxi-
not the beta, the beta
method of solution
is applicable to something called
Heisenberg ferromagnets, not to the
Ising ferromagnet.
No.
You described this in terms of
gas-liquid phase transition. Is it
equally applicable to liquid-solid phase
No.
Li- the liquid-solid phase transition
is a transition
from a
homogeneous
uh configuration to one which is
crystallized
where all the molecules line up in a in
a definite lattice.
And it's a sharp transition where the
system goes from a disordered liquid
phase to a sharply ordered lattice
configuration.
Now, the problem with this system and
the reason that it can't exhibit that
kind of phase transition because it's
already biased by having its own lattice
and there's no sharp transition between
a lattice uh symmetry and no lattice
symmetry because it's already got its
built-in lattice structure. So, no,
there is no uh there is no
um
no notion of a solid-liquid phase
transition for this system. Okay. And
then a related question with gas-liquid,
does that mean if you put a liquid
through a very small capillary, you
can't tell whether it's a liquid or a
gas?
Cuz that's effectively one way to I
would have said if you put it above the
phase tran- above the uh critical point,
you can't tell if it's a liquid or a
gas. Um
uh
No, I think the the Okay.
I think you're
you're right. If you put take a small
enough sample, you can't tell if it's a
liquid or gas.
Phase transitions
are things that happen in the infinite
number of and the limit of infinite
number of particles.
Phase transitions never happen for
finite number of degrees of freedom.
For finite number of degrees of freedom,
there are never sharp phase transitions
or sharp discontinuities.
And the way you can see that is you can
look at the structure of the partition
function.
The structure of the partition function,
when you have finite number of degrees
of freedom
the partition function is a finite sum
over finitely many uh particles, and if
it's a spin system like that over
finitely many configurations
of e to the minus beta times the energy.
Each contribution from every single
state is an analytic smooth function of
beta. And when you add up a finite
number of analytic or smooth functions,
you get a smooth function.
Phase transitions are
singularities, places of discontinuity
of some sort as a function of
temperature.
So, for finite number of degrees of
freedom, you never get phase
transitions. There are never the so- the
the partition function is always
completely analytic. It takes an
infinite number of degrees of freedom
uh basically, these sums have to be
infinite sums, and if the spins only
take on values of 1 and minus 1
well, you'll have to have an infinite
number of spins before this can add up
to something singular.
So, right. So, in fact, you cannot tell
the difference between a gas and a
liquid at any temperature except maybe
zero temperature, but let's forget that.
Uh at any temperature, you can't tell
the difference between a gas and a
liquid or or or any of these things
um by looking at small samples. It takes
large samples uh to
And then even if the sample is very,
very large
uh its magnetization
is
not infinitely stable
unless it's infinitely
uh infinitely big. It just requires an
infinite background to hold the whole
thing together. So,
uh
So, there's two different ways in two
different situations where you can't
tell the difference between a gas and a
liquid. One of them is just studying
small samples.
Okay? The other
is when you have a critical point like
this and you go around the critical
point, there's no sharp place where you
go from gas to liquid.
The properties sort of smoothly go from
one to the other.
Yeah. Could I wonder if you could
remind us exactly how the thermodynamics
of this
of this particle is. We've got it going
back to like the baths, each particle is
thought of as a as a as a
one of the baths which is in
equilibrium.
Well, I wouldn't call the rest of these
heat baths. I would just call it the
mean field uh The reason I wouldn't call
it heat bath
field bath would still have to
In order to apply
the Boltzmann statistics, so we have to
exchange energy with it. It's
with the with the surroundings in some
way, don't we?
Yeah.
So, what does that mean exactly? Okay,
it means that there are other little
terms in the energy
which cause, when you put them into the
equations of motion of the system
cause transfer of energy back and forth.
Now, we haven't talked about this, but I
will I will discuss it for a moment now.
Um
If you have a system whose energy
Let's use the language of quantum spins
now, okay?
Language of quantum spins. If
So, sigma then has three components,
sigma 1, sigma 2, and sigma 3.
The sigma that we've been talking about
here could be the Z component, the third
component of the spin.
And there would be a term in the energy
which would just be proportional to
sigma 3 of one particle times sigma 3 of
another particle.
With a minus sign.
All right.
Uh
From the point of view of the mechanics
of the quantum mechanics of this system
sigma 3 will never change with time.
There's nothing in Think of this as a
Hamiltonian.
There's nothing in this Hamiltonian
which doesn't commute with sigma 3. In
fact, the only things in the Hamiltonian
are sigma 3.
There's nothing which doesn't commute.
Now, I'll remind you because I know
you've studied quantum mechanics at
least a little bit
that the time derivative of something Do
you remember the formula for the time
derivative of a quantity?
Yeah, I just did the commutator. The
commutator with the Hamiltonian. Do you
remember that?
Okay? So, the commutator of I times the
commutator Is it A with H or H with A? I
don't remember. But, that's good enough.
There's nothing in this system here
which does not commute with sigma 3. So,
what this means is if this system if you
were to lay it down and lay down a given
configuration, it would never change.
It's completely static. There's nothing
in it which would allow it to change. Of
course, that also means it would never
come to thermal equilibrium. You need a
little bit of interaction of a different
kind, something which doesn't commute
with these sigmas.
So, you could add
something like a tiny, tiny little
number epsilon
times the first component of sigma 1
sigma I times
first component, sorry, sigma 1
sigma 1 of J and maybe another one with
sigma 2 and so forth. You'd have to add
something in
that doesn't commute with the sigma 3s
to give it time dependence.
As it is
it doesn't have any time dependence, but
you always imagine in your back of your
mind that there are tiny little
interactions between things which can
cause them to change. This system as it
as it stands doesn't have anything in it
which would tell you how things change
with time.
You know what it's like? It's like
having an expression for the energy in
classical mechanics which only had
potential energy.
No kinetic energy.
If a system didn't have any kinetic
energy, it wouldn't move.
It would have energy depending on its
position, but it wouldn't have anything
It would have no
nothing in its dynamics which would
cause it to move from point to point.
So, you can think of this
here
the term that we included
as the potential energy
of this lattice of molecules, the
ignoring the kinetic energy which causes
things to change. So, there are no that
that that additional kinetic energy is
going
allow these things to stick get into
some sort of equilibrium.
Yeah, it allows them to get into
equilibrium. It allows them to change
with time. They're approaching each
equilibrium. But interestingly enough,
it has no effect whatever on on the
phase diagram, on the
on the nature of phase transitions.
That's all determined by potential
energy.
Uh
and surprisingly,
kinetic energy doesn't play any role in
these phase transitions.
Uh the system finds the configuration,
well,
the potential kinetic energy doesn't
play any role. Only can
No. Kinetic energy doesn't play any
role. So So in the end, we find the
thing
up with the probability to beta PS and
down with the
with the
Now, but you must always imagine, as you
say, you must always imagine there's a
little more to the system which must be
very weak in order that the energetics
is mostly dominated by the things you've
kept. But you must always imagine
there's a little more which brings the
system to thermal equilibrium. What I'm
I guess what I'm wondering about is
are there subsystems that you might
think you could model this way that
you'd go wrong if you didn't?
I can't think of any offhand.
Uh
So this is quite a quite a general
class of uh
Well,
if we tried to use this to describe how
a fluid flows out of a little um
uh hole in a container
and how the fluid
goes from inside the container to
outside the container, it would never do
that.
We could never Yeah, we could never
study
the approach to thermal equilibrium or
the approach to anything. So we would
completely fail to study anything that
that involves the time dependence of the
system.
All we can study is the equilibrium
properties.
Um
but I think you're asking whether there
are systems whose equilibrium properties
wouldn't be correctly described this
way. Well, I I'm sure we can invent
them. Yes, we can certainly invent them.
Any mixing in the Hamiltonian between
kinetic and potential terms, between
position and momentum will
uh
Uh the reason we get away with this is
because the energy consists of two
pieces, one which is completely
potential and only depends on the
positions, and the other which is
completely kinetic and only depends on
the momenta.
Remember, the partition function is an
integral over positions and momenta.
The
the potential energy doesn't make
the the integrations over the momenta
don't care about the potential energies,
and they just factor off completely.
They just factor off and they're exactly
the same as if the molecules weren't
interacting with each other.
The potential terms are the things which
know about the interaction between
molecules. The other term the other
factor doesn't.
And so all of the properties of the gas
which are interesting with respect to
the phase transitions and so forth have
to do with potential energy.
Crystallization has nothing to do with
potential kinetic energy. All it has to
do with is finding the the
configurations of molecules
which form crystal lattices, and that's
got entirely to do with potential
energy.
Minimizing a certain combination of
potential energy and entropy.
Yeah, a couple of weeks ago you were
describing coarse and fine grain
entropy, and
I can't remember that you said in coarse
grain entropy that the
um
Liouville
uh theorem is violated.
No, I didn't say the Liouville theorem
is never violated.
No, it's a theorem. Theorems can't be
violated. Theorems are either wrong or
right. The theorem is never violated.
That's why I think we're saying that
when the Liouville strands get really
skinny and you have a
you have a delta P delta X that's wider
than that, then
that doesn't violate the uh
No, because the Liouville theorem is not
about coarse graining.
It's just not about coarse graining.
It's about fine grain system.
It's just not a theorem about the coarse
grain
entropy.
It's a strictly a theorem about the fine
grain entropy. So how could coarse
graining violate the theorem about fine
grain entropy? That's my
understanding of the relation, but
Okay? But you might have imagined a
wrong Liouville theorem which says that
the fine grained entropy doesn't change,
that the volume of Sorry, the coarse
grained entropy doesn't change.
That would not be a theorem. It's
violated, but it wouldn't be a theorem,
and nobody ever thought it would be a
theorem.
Right. Okay. What?
So if I announce the new theorem,
this is the Schmouville theorem or the
Louisville theorem the Lou the
Louisville theorem
the Louisville Slugger who invented the
Louisville theorem said that the volume
in phase and coarse grained phase space
is constant with time.
Well, that that would have been
violated. Yeah. But what would be the
thing you explained what happens when
the
when
um the phase space as
things turn into the
the area turns into a very
wavy kind of uh
you know, cotton candy kind of thing,
and then you have
uh we're we're talking about coarse
grain Well, okay. So I say, take that
cotton cotton candy
and look at the volume actually
occupied
by the candy. It's very tiny.
Very tiny. But on the other hand, if you
were to take every little
spot along the fibers and put on that
spot a little ball about that big.
Of course, they would crash into each
other, but but if they crash into each
other, just let them overlap. And to
take the volume that would be carved out
by this coarse grained version of the
cotton candy, where every point is
blurred over a certain size, it would
fill up the area that you that you you
know, the pink
the pink
cloud of uh
Right. So there are two different
descriptions of volume. One of them is
the coarse grained volume, where you
you know, where you um
I don't know what the right word is.
Coarse grained is the word. But where
you let each little piece of the cotton
be replaced by a little sphere, and the
spheres eventually the cotton will get
so close together that the little
spheres will begin to overlap. And those
little spheres will fill up the volume
that visually you would see in this
cloud of cotton candy. Much bigger
volume.
So
as the cotton candy is spun out,
it starts as a little glob of sugar that
big.
And if you coarse grain a little glob of
sugar that big, it's that big. Not much
bigger. And now it starts to spread out
its tentacles in all directions and
create this cloud of cotton candy.
But now you replace each point along
that fibrous structure with a little
sphere, it'll occupy a volume which is
much bigger. So as you spin out the
cotton candy, it seems to grow, although
the actual volume of sugar is exactly
the same.
That's what happens.
Cotton candy, that's a good example.
Right. That's a very good example. I
will use it next time.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.